Soviet Union and Russia Jehovah’s Witnesses Subject Files, Inclusive: 1955-2001, undated, Bulk: 1971-1999
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union and Russia Jehovah’s Witnesses Subject Files
Inclusive: 1955-2001, undated, Bulk: 1971-1999
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
23
Keston Institute, 1969 -
1.5 A4 Document Boxes
The Soviet Union and Russia Jehovah’s Witnesses Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the history and persecution of Jehovah’s Witnesses in the former Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
In the early 1960s, Keston began collecting materials on the persecution of Jehovah’s Witnesses in the Soviet Union.
Jehovah’s Witnesses have been present in the Russian Empire at least since the end of the nineteenth century. In 1891, Charles Tate Russel, the founder of the movement, travelled to Russia where he met with several members. In the 1920s, larger groups and individual congregations of Jehovah’s Witnesses began forming. In 1940, their number significantly grew after the annexation of Western Ukraine and Bessarabia, which is now a part of Moldova, territories with established Jehovah’s Witnesses congregations. In the mid-1980s, the main centers of the movement were in Belorussia, Moldavia, and Ukraine.
Jehovah’s Witnesses organizations and activities have been banned in the former Soviet Union. Authorities accused members of following orders of their American “masters,” engaging in spying and anti-Communist activities, refusing to serve in the Soviet army, and illegal Bible smuggling. The government launched an aggressive campaign against the movement in the media. Its members were arrested, imprisoned, and exiled to Middle Asia and Far East.
In December 1991, under the 1990 law on Religious Freedom and Religious Organizations, Jehovah’s Witnesses finally received legal registration. However, even after the collapse of Communism, persecution continued. The 1997 Russian law on Freedom of Conscience and Religious Association acknowledged Christianity, Islam, Buddhism, and Judaism as historically traditional religions in the Russian Federation. The law also set a new system for state registration of religious organization that made refusing or revoking registration of “not traditional” religions and denominations easier. The new law significantly affected Jehovah’s Witnesses because the denomination was considered a Western Christian religious organization of marginal faith. Numerous court cases resulted.
A new wave of persecution began in 2009, after the Russian State Duma passed amendments to the 2002 Law on Countermeasures against Extremist Activity. Under the law, local government authorities began investigating Jehovah’s Witnesses’ literature and activities for extremism. In 2012, the government adopted new rules and regulations for nonprofit organizations which directly affected the group. The global organization headquartered in the United States received “foreign agent” status which subjected its members to legal and administrative measures. Five years later, the Russian Supreme Court declared Jehovah’s Witnesses an extremist sect. In August 2017, the Russian Department of Justice added them to the list of banned organizations. Under Russian laws, Jehovah’s Witnesses face ongoing persecution from authorities and hostility from citizens who consider them a dangerous sect that harms families and spreads religious hatred.
Scope and Content
Jehovah’s Witnesses materials consist of bibliographic references, periodical clippings, manuscripts, reports, copies of court documents and legal paperwork, and print materials.
The materials cover the period from 1955 to 2001 and include general information on the history and persecution of Jehovah’s Witnesses in the former Soviet Union with a focus on the influence that changes in Russian religious laws had on the movement in post-Soviet Russia. The files contain clippings from the Soviet and Russian press as a part of the government’s aggressive information campaign against the Witnesses. Court reports and legal documents pertain to the Golovinskii trial in Moscow in the late 1990s and several individual cases, including the struggle to register a local Jehovah’s Witnesses organization in Lipetsk. The files also include some Jehovah’s Witnesses publications and print materials.
Arrangement
Keston received Jehovah’s Witnesses materials in unprocessed files. The materials were organized thematically and chronologically.
The Soviet Union and Russia Jehovah’s Witnesses Subject Files are currently arranged into one series: I. General
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 23.
Related Resources
Related references
Baran, Emily B. Dissent on the Margins: How Soviet Jehovah’s Witnesses Defied Communism and Lived to Preach about It. New York, NY: Oxford University Press, 2014. [newspaper]
Bourdeaux, Michael., and Filatov, S. B. Sovremennai︠a︡ religioznai︠a︡ zhizn)' Rossii: opyt sistematicheskogo opisanii︠a︡. Moskva: “Logos,” 2004.
Index Terms
Places
Russia (Federation) -- Church history -- 20th century.; Soviet Union -- Church history -- 20th century.
Subjects
Christianity and atheism.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Jehovah's Witnesses -- Persecutions.; Jehovah's Witnesses -- Russia (Federation) -- History -- 20th century.; Jehovah's Witnesses -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.; Jehovah's Witnesses -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Legal instruments.; Manuscripts.; Persecution -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.; Records (Documents); Religion and state -- Russia (Federation) -- History -- 20th century.; Religion and state -- Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century.
Genres
Persecution -- Russia (Federation) -- History -- 20th century.
- General, 1955-2001; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains information on the everyday life and struggle of Jehovah’s Witnesses in the former Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia, including trial reports, court documents, and newspaper articles. The series is in good condition.
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. General (1 of 6), 1955-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. General (2 of 6), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. General (3 of 6), 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. General (4 of 6), 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. General (5 of 6), 1980-2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. General (6 of 6), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - State Oppressive Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses. Public Attacks in the Media, 1962-1966, 1970-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - State Oppressive Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses. Trials and Imprisonments, 1962-1963, 1974-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - State Oppressive Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses. Golovinskii Trial (1 of 3), 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - State Oppressive Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses. Golovinskii Trial (2 of 3), 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - State Oppressive Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses. Golovinskii Trial (3 of 3), 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - State Oppressive Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses. N. Nikishina Case, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Life of Jehovah's Witnesses Congregations, 1962, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses. Activities Disapproved by State, 1963, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jehovah's Witnesses Theology, Philosophy, Education Ethics, 1963, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - World Practices toward Jehovah's Witnesses., 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Information Campaign against Jehovah's Witnesses., 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Documents and Reports Pertaining to Persecution of Jehovah's Witnesses in Russia, 1997-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Documents and Materials on the Court Case over Refusal to Register a Local Jehovah's Witnesses Congregation in Lipetsk, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Print Materials, 1994-2000, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)